Guide to the Albert Rich Brand papers, 1928-1940.
Brand, Albert Rich papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Albert Rich Brand papers, 1928-1940.
21-18-899
Brand, Albert Rich.
1.5 cubic ft.
48 phonograph records
Correspondence, printed materials, publications, research materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Brand's papers relating to ornithology.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Ornithologist.
Research associate, Cornell University; ornithologist at the American Museum of Natural History. Brand was born in 1889 and died in 1940.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Brand's correspondence (1928-40) with Arthur A. Allen, Peter Paul Kellogg, Herbert Sanborn of Vanderbilt University, Dr. Frank E. Lutz, curator of the Museum, and others, mainly concerning his pioneering work recording the songs and calls of American wild birds and his ornithological writing; drafts and reprints of his articles and speeches (1930-38); typescript notes (1930-39) titled "Bird Diaries" and "Bird Hearing Experiment"; typescripts and photographs (one bound volume) describing the Cornell-American Museum of Natural History Ornithological Expedition of 1935, as well as letters from Allen and Kellogg to Brand during and after the expedition; correspondence of Herbert J. Seligmann with Brand's widow, Ernestine I. Brand, and others concerning his proposed biography of Brand and drafts of the first four chapters of this book; other biographical data, including a scrapbook of clippings concerning Brand; photographs, correspondence, and printed items concerning ornithological meetings; and lists of his publications. Includes a leather-bound book entitled "Hunting with a Mike" that was issued in 1935 to the members of the Cornell sound expedition, with a photographic and text account of the trip. The collection also includes 48 phonograph recordings of birds and frogs made Brand including two put out by the American Foundation for the Blind. Also, thesis, Recording Bird Songs, 1932.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Brand, Albert Rich.; Allen, Arthur A. (Arthur Augustus), 1885-1964.; Brand, Ernestine I.; Kellogg, Peter Paul, 1899-1975; Lutz, Frank Eugene, 1879-1943.; Sanborn, Herbert.; Seligmann, Herbert J.; American Museum of Natural History.; Cornell University -- Faculty.
Subjects:
Birds -- United States.; Bird-song -- Recording and reproducing.; Ornithology.; Scientific expeditions.; Ornithologists.
Form and Genre Terms:
Biographies.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Phonograph records.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIAL
The Peter Paul Kellogg papers, #21-18-893, contain recordings made by Brand.
The James Taylor Tanner papers, #21-18-1362 and the Arthur Augustus Allen papers, #21-18-1255 contain additional materials about the Laboratory of Ornithology and the 1935 Cornell-American Museum of Natural History Ornithological Expedition.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Professional Papers
  - Manuscripts of articles by Brand, 1930-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence regarding articles
  - Manuscripts of articles by Brand - B-H, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Manuscripts of Articles by Brand - H-S, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence used by Seligmann in his book about Brand, September 1934-June 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Chapter I; first draft - Biography of Albert R. Brand by H.J. Seligmann, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chapter II; first draft - Biography of Albert R. Brand by H.J. Seligmann, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chapter III; first draft - Biography of Albert R. Brand by H.J. Seligmann, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chapter IV; first draft - Biography of Albert R. Brand by H.J. Seligmann, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chapter I; second draft - Biography of Albert R. Brand by H.J. Seligmann, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chapter II; second draft - Biography of Albert R. Brand by H.J. Seligmann, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chapter III; second draft - Biography of Albert R. Brand by H.J. Seligmann, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chapter IV; second draft - Biography of Albert R. Brand by H.J. Seligmann, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Extra Reprints by Albert R. Brand, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "For Connie to read", 1932-1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Includes manuscripts of radio talks and articles as well as a reprint by Arthur Allen
  - "For Connie to read", 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Laboratory of Ornithology Newsletters that mention Brand, a reprint by Peter Paul Kellogg and a report on the recordings of wild birds by Brand.
  - Talks and speeches by Albert R. Brand, 1932-1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Talks and speeches by Albert R. Brand, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon by Elsa G. Allen, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 13th International Ornithological Congress, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Special articles about and by Brand, 1927-1957 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - A memoir of American Ornithologists Union, Charleston, N.C., 1937 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Notice of admission to Cornell, etc., 1929-1937 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - General Correspondence, 1928-1931 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - General Correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - General Correspondence, January-September 1933 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - General Correspondence, September 1933-January 1935 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - General Correspondence, March 1936-April 1937 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - General Correspondence, May 1937-December 1938 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - General Correspondence, January 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bird Diary 1, February 1930-February 1931 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Bird Diary 1, February-June 1931 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Bird Diary 1 and Index, June-November 1931 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bird Diary 2, January-November 1932 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Bird Diary 2, December-May 1934 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Bird Diary 3, April 1935-March 1937 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Bird Diary 3, March-May 1937 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Bird Diary 3, June-December 1937 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Bird Diary 4: Bird hearing experiment, March-July 1938 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Bird Diary 4: Bird hearing experiment, July 1938-July 1939 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence - Cornell American Museum Expedition, January-April 1935 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence - Cornell American Museum Expedition, April-August 1935 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Special letters relating to Albert R. Brand and bird recording, 1929-1940 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Information gathered by Brand for the National Cyclopedia of American Biography, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence - Rouen; Paris, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    International Ornithological Congress meeting
  - Rouen; Paris, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Itinerary, expenses, correspondence and programs for events
  - Oxford, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Misc. Correspondence, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Reprints; Lists of Publications, 1933-1936 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Reprints; Lists of Publications, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Handwritten Bird Diaries, February 1930-June 1933 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Handwritten Bird Diaries, September 1933-August 1935 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Handwritten Bird Diaries, February 1937-July 1939 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    June-July 1937 in another folder
  - Handwritten Bird Diaries, June-July 1937 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Bird Roll Call and Journal, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    By species
  - Bird Logs, 1932-1932 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - "An Informal Report of the First Year's Work in an Experiment in Recording the Songs of Wild Birds" - Thesis by Brand, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    Photocopy
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
    Mainly taken on recording trips with Arthur Allen. Photos include Arthur Allen, Peter Paul Kellogg, Elsa Guerdrum Allen, Herbert Friedman, and Charles Brand
  - Notebook of newspaper clippings, 1921-1940 (Box 2)
  - Hunting with a Mike by Albert R. Brand, 1935 (Box 2)
    Bound book of the Cornell/Museum of Natural History expedition. Includes photos of the people involved with the expedition and their activities, including George Miksch Sutton, George Lowery, J. J. Kuhn, and others. Also includes photos of the ivory billed wood pecker.
  - American Ornithologists' Union, Chicago, 1934-10-23-1934-10-25 (Folder 1)
    Photograph
  - American Ornithologists' Union, 53rd Stated Meeting, Undated (Folder 1)
  - Group photo (unidentified), 1938 (Folder 1)
  - 50th Anniversery American Ornithologists' Union, Museum of Natural History, New York, 1933 (Folder 1)
- Series II. Sound Recordings
  - Songs of Wild Birds, undated; 5501-5502 (Box 3)
  - Frogs, undated; 5503-5507 & 5544-5548 (Box 3)
  - Leach's Petrel, 1937; 5508-5511 & 5543 (Box 3)
    Date and title are engraved in the center of the record.
  - Kirkland's Warbler, 1937; 5512-5522 (Box 3)
  - 3A: Eastern Meadowlark, Western Meadowlark, Dickcissel, White-eyed Vireo, B.C. Chickadee, Nighthawk, undated; 5523 (Box 3)
  - 3A (Second Best): Eastern Meadowlark, Western Meadowlark, Dickcissel, White-eyed Vireo, B.C. Chickadee, Nighthawk, undated; 5524 (Box 3)
  - 3B (1st Set): House Finch, Purple Finch, Orchard Oriole, Warbling Vireo, (Flicker Call), Red-eyed Vireo, Blue-headed Vireo, Yellow-throated Vireo, undated; 5525 (Box 3)
  - 3B (2nd Set): House Finch, Purple Finch, Orchard Oriole, Warbling Vireo, (Flicker Call), Red-eyed Vireo, Blue-headed Vireo, Yellow-throated Vireo, undated; 5526 (Box 3)
  - 3B (Badly Scratched): House Finch, Purple Finch, Orchard Oriole, Warbling Vireo, (Flicker Call), Red-eyed Vireo, Blue-headed Vireo, Yellow-throated Vireo, undated; 5527 (Box 3)
  - 4A (1st Set): Canada Warbler, Ruby-crowned Kinglet, Hooded Warbler, Kentucky Warbler, Ovenbird, Piliated Woodpecker, Barred Owl, undated; 5528 (Box 3)
  - 4A (2nd Best): Canada Warbler, Ruby-crowned Kinglet, Hooded Warbler, Kentucky Warbler, Ovenbird, Piliated Woodpecker, Barred Owl, undated; 5529 (Box 3)
  - 4B: Spring Morning, Bull Frog, Blue Jay, Red-wing Blackbird, Spring Peepers, Pied-billed Grebe, Crested Flycatcher, Downy Woodpecker, Yellow-billed Sapsucker, Flicker, undated; 5530 (Box 3)
  - 4B (Second Best): Spring Morning, Bull Frog, Blue Jay, Red-wing Blackbird, Spring Peepers, Pied-billed Grebe, Crested Flycatcher, Downy Woodpecker, Yellow-billed Sapsucker, Flicker, undated; 5531 (Box 3)
  - 5A: Chirping Sparrow, Swamp Sparrow, Red-winged Blackbird, Pine Woods Sparrow, Bluebird, Towhee, Spotted Towhee, Chuck-will's Widow, undated; 5532 (Box 3)
  - 5A: Chirping Sparrow, Swamp Sparrow, Red-winged Blackbird, Pine Woods Sparrow, Bluebird, Towhee, Spotted Towhee, Chuck-will's Widow, undated; 5533 (Box 3)
  - Kirkland's Warbler - Test, undated; 5534 (Box 3)
  - Virginia's Warbler, undated; 5535 (Box 3)
  - unlabelled, undated; 5536 (Box 3)
  - Kirkland's Warbler (copy of the 1937 recording), undated; 5537 (Box 3)
    "To Paul with my compliments, yes compliments!" Albert
  - Page 2: Birds of the North Woods, undated; 5538 (Box 3)
  - Page 3: Birds of the North Woods, undated; 5539 (Box 3)
  - Page 4: Birds of the North Woods, undated; 5540 (Box 3)
  - "Talking Book (Solely for the use of the Blind): Birds of the North Woods, Part 2, undated; 5541 (Box 3)
  - "Talking Book (Solely for the use of the Blind): Wild Birds and Their Songs, Part 3 & 4, undated; 5542 (Box 3)